Finding Aid for Warren E. Miller Papers 1950-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren E. Miller Papers 1950-1980
Miller, Warren E. (Warren Edward), 1924-
3.75 linear feet
Director of the University of Michigan Center for Political Studies at the Institute of Social Research, 1970-1981, later program director of the Center for Political Studies; files relating to his education and to his career at the University of Michigan.
99109 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were received in December 1995-February 1996 as part of several accessions from the Institute of Social Research of the University of Michigan. Donor no. 3563
The collection is open for research.
Warren Edward Miller was born March 26, 1924 in Howarden, Iowa. After serving in the United States Army Air Force from 1943 to 1946, he attended the University of Oregon, where he received his B.A. in political science in 1948 and M.A. in political science in 1950. He continued his studies at the Maxwell Graduate School of Citizenship and Public Affairs at Syracuse University, where he received his Ph.D. in political science in 1954. In 1951 Miller began work with the Survey Research Center at the Institute of Social Research at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. There he acted as assistant study director, 1951-1953, study director, 1953-1956, research associate, 1956-1959, program director, 1959-1968, research coordinator of the political behavior program, 1968-1970, and principle investigator of national election studies first beginning in 1977. In addition, Miller served as the director of the Center for Political Studies at the Institute of Social Research, 1970-1981 and then program director of the Center for Political Studies, beginning in 1982.
In 1954 Miller left the University of Michigan to become an assistant professor of political science at the University of California at Berkeley. He returned to the University of Michigan in June of 1956, however, where in addition to his continued work at the Survey Research Center he taught in the political science department. Miller acted as assistant professor of political science, 1956-1958, associate professor of political science, 1958-63, and professor of political science, 1963-1993. Beginning in 1981 Miller also acted as professor of political science at Arizona State University, where in 1988 he was made Regents' professor.
Warren Miller was active in a number of professional associations throughout his career, including the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the International Political Science Association, the Midwest Political Science Association, the International Society of Political Psychology, and the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, of which he was a fellow from 1961 to 1962. Miller served as executive director of the Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research from 1962 to 1970, and associate director of that same organization beginning in 1978. He also served as president of the American Political Science Association from 1979 to 1980, and president of the Social Science History Association from 1979 to 1980. Miller's extensive duties took him to conferences and meetings throughout the United States and Europe.
During the course of his career Miller conducted much research in the areas of individual voter behavior and participation in national politics, reception of and reaction to communications concerning political events, and the representational process which links constituents and their elected representatives. His research led to a vast amount of publications. Books of which he was either sole author or contributor include The Voter Decides (1954), American Voter (1960), Elections and the Political Order (1966), Leadership and Change: Presidential Elections from 1952-1976 (1977), Parties in Transition (1986), Without Consent (1988), The American National Election Studies Data Sourcebook, 1952-78 (1980), and The American National Election Studies Data Sourcebook, 1952-86 (1989). In addition, Miller contributed articles to a number of professional publications. He served on the editorial board of a number of these, including the American Political Science Review, 1966-1971, Computers and the Humanities, 1969-1971, Social Science History, 1976-1991, Social Science Review, 1973, and the Sage Electoral Studies Yearbook, 1974.
Miller's distinguished career in political science was recognized through a number of honors. He received the Distinguished Alumnus award from the Maxwell School for Citizenship and Public Affairs of Syracuse University in 1974, the Distinguished Faculty Achievement award from the University of Michigan in 1977, and the Distinguished Professor Award from Arizona State University in 1981. He was further honored by the creation of the Warren E. Miller Award for Intellectual Accomplishment and Service by the American Political Science Association in 1995, and the creation of the Warren E. Miller Award for Meritorious Service by the Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research in 1993.
Miller died January 30, 1999 in Scottsdale, Arizona at the age of 74.
The Warren Miller Papers document Miller's time spent fulfilling his many roles at the University of Michigan. The bulk of the materials span the 1950s and 1960s, and include materials relating to courses he taught, administrative duties he performed both as a member of the political science department and conducting the work of the Survey Research Center, and research he conducted. The collection is arranged into four series: Biographical/ Personal (1956-1976); Education (1950-1954); University of Michigan (1955-1980); and Correspondence (1954-1967)
Subjects:
Miller, Warren E. (Warren Edward), 1924-1999; Elections.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan. Survey Research Center.
- Biographical /Personal
  The Biographical/ Personal series, approximately 0.1 linear feet, includes biographical information in the form of curricula vitae, bibliography, and short narrative biographical descriptions, created at differing stages in Miller's career. It also includes a possibly unpublished paper given by Miller at a professional association meeting.
  - Biographical information (includes documents dated 1956-1976) (Box 1)
  - Paper given at the American Association for the Advancement of Science meeting, Indianapolis entitled "The Socio-Economic Analysis of Political Behavior" December 1957 (Box 1)
- Education
  The Education series, approximately 0.1 linear feet, includes materials relating to Miller's own education. It includes materials relating to the completion of his doctoral thesis at Syracuse University, as well as materials relating to courses Miller completed at the University of Michigan in the summer of 1950, including notes, exams, and study materials/syllabus information.
  - Doctoral thesis (correspondence pertaining to) 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Psychology 233 Summer 1950 (Box 1)
  - Psychology 246 Summer 1950 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series, approximately 2.55 linear feet, is comprised of four subseries, Course Materials, Administrative files, Requests for Funds, and Conferences/Meetings which together give insight into Miller's various commitments, responsibilities, and activities at the university.
  - Course Materials
    The Course Materials subseries is ordered numerically by course number and then chronologically by term and year taught (if available), and includes materials such as syllabi, assigned reading lists, exams, assignments, and miscellaneous materials used in the teaching of the course. Materials cover classes taught from 1957 to 1980.
    - Summer Institute on Survey Research 1957 (Box 1)
    - Summer Institute on Survey Research 1958 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 115 (Psychology and Politics)
      - Fall 1956 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1957 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1958 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1959 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 116 (Public Opinion and Pressure Groups)
      - Spring 1961 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 161 Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 164 Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 201
      - Fall 1955 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1957 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1958 (Box 1)
      - Spring 1959 (Box 1)
      - Spring 1960 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1960 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 224 Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 300 (Contemporary Political Issues)
      - Fall 1974 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1976 (Box 1)
      - Winter 1976 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1978 (Box 1)
      - Fall 1980 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Political Science 315 Spring 1958 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 320 Fall 1972 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 326 (Political Parties: Organization and Methods)
      - Fall 1958 (Box 1)
      - Summer 1959 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Political Science 486 (Public Opinion and Pressure Groups) Spring 1963 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 681 Fall 1969 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 687 Summer 1969 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 697 Fall 1969 (Box 1)
    - Political Science 783 Winter 1972 (Box 1)
    - Political Science Miscellaneous Course Syllabi 1964-1971 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Files
    The Administrative files subseries is divided into Department of Political Science, Survey Research Center, and Detroit Area Study. Department of Political Science files are arranged alphabetically by topic, and include materials relating to departmental concerns and activities: department chairmanship, faculty evaluations, graduate degree committees, methods, preliminary examinations, and subfield structure. Following these are Survey Research Center administrative files, which consists of materials relating to the business of the Center such as memos, delineation of policies and procedures, and various committee reports. These are arranged chronologically by year, spanning 1950 to 1960. Following this is one folder of materials relating to the Detroit Area Study, a research study with which Miller was involved. Materials relate primarily to the preliminary organization and planning of the project, 1958-1960, by the executive committee.
    - Department of Political Science
      - Course Offerings 1972 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Evaluations 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Evaluations 1974-1977 (Box 1)
      - Methods 1974-1977 (Box 1)
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Chairmanship 1969-1970 (Box 2)
      - Department Chairmanship 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Degree Committees 1957-1961 (Box 2)
      - Graduate Student Placement 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Guidelines for Graduate Program 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Political Behavior Program Students 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Preliminary Examinations 1968-1974 (Box 2)
      - Stokes' Replacement Committee 1971 (Box 2)
      - Screening Examinations 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Subfield Structure (restructuring of departmental subfields) 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - Survey Research Center
      - 1950-1960, 10 folders (Box 2)
        missing 1955
    - Detroit Area Study 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Requests for Funding
    Requests for Funds is the next subseries in the University of Michigan series, which is organized chronologically and includes materials and correspondence relating to grant proposals or other requests for funding by Miller for various projects.
    - 1955 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Conferences/Meetings
    The final subseries is Conferences/Meetings which contains materials from the many professional conferences and meetings Miller attended throughout his career at the University of Michigan. These materials are ordered chronologically and then by the name of the conference (in the case of annual conferences) spanning the years 1961 to 1979.
    - International Political Science Association 5th World Conference, Paris 1961 (Box 2)
    - International Political Science Association 6th World Conference, Geneva 1964 (Box 2)
    - International Political Science Association 7th World Conference, Brussels 1967 (Box 2)
    - International Political Science Association 8th World Conference 1970 (Box 2)
    - Social Science Research Council Conference on "Uses of Survey Research in the Study of Political Modernization" May 1963 (Box 2)
    - International Conference on Corporate Political Sociology, Tampere August, 1963 (Box 2)
    - "Policy Representation and Congress," International Affairs Seminar of Washington 1964 (Box 2)
    - International Social Science Council 2nd Archival Meeting, Paris 1964 (Box 2)
    - International Social Science Council 3rd Archival Meeting, London 1965 (Box 2)
    - American Association for Public Opinion Research, Groton Connecticut May 15, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Foundation for Research on Human Behavior, Seminar on Political Issues and Business in 1964 (Box 2)
    - Second European Seminar on the Uses of Survey Data, Amsterdam 1966 (Box 3)
    - International Social Science Council Symposium on Quantitative Ecological Analysis in the Social Sciences, Evian 1966 (Box 3)
    - International Conference on Comparative Electoral Behavior, Ann Arbor 1967 (Box 3)
    - Judicial Behavior Conference, Princeton 1967 (Box 3)
    - Computers and International Relations, Oak Ridge, Tennessee 1967 (Box 3)
    - Electoral Systems Symposium, Bad Godesberg 1968 (Box 3)
    - UNESCO Symposium on Nation Building, Gothenberg, Sweden 1968 (Box 3)
    - International Social Science Council Conference on Secondary Analysis, Cologne May 1969 (Box 3)
    - Conference on Comparative Parliamentary Behavior, Netherlands April 1970 (Box 3)
    - UNESCO Nation Building Conference, Cerisy, France August 1970 (Box 3)
    - Workshop on Indicators of National Development August 1971 (Box 3)
    - Center for Political Studies French Data Conference September 1971 (Box 3)
    - Baconian Dialogues, The University of Minnesota, Minneapolis October 1972 (Box 3)
    - 50th Anniversary of Maxwell School, Syracuse University October 1973 (Box 3)
    - Library of Congress Seminar 1974 (Box 3)
    - First Sangamon State Public Affairs Colloquium "Crisis in Confidence," Springfield, Illinois January 1974 (Box 3)
    - ECPR Workshop "Participation, Voting, and Party Competition" 1974 (Box 3)
    - American Political Science Association 70th Annual Meeting, Chicago 1974 (Box 3)
    - Judicial Behavior Conference, Detroit 1974 (Box 3)
    - American Enterprise Institute "Recent Political Trends in Scandinavia," Washington, D.C. 1975 (Box 3)
    - Conference on Electoral Studies, Nuffield College, Oxford, England April 1975 (Box 3)
    - Milton C. Cummings Lectureship, Johns Hopkins University October 1975 (Box 3)
    - Midwest Political Science Association 1976 (Box 3)
    - APSA Paper 1977 (Box 3)
    - APSA Research for Paper, Fall 1978 (Box 3)
    - Local Party Organization Conference May 1980 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1966-1979 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, approximately 1 linear foot, is divided into two subseries. The first is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and includes correspondence with specific colleagues or organizations and reviews of manuscripts and grant proposals during the years from 1954 to 1977. The second is arranged chronologically, and spans the years from 1956 to 1966. This includes correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, with colleagues and organizations on such topics as publications, research ideas, and future plans.
  - Topical
    - American Political Science Association (APSA) Program Committee 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - Brookings Institute, The 1955-1956 (Box 3)
    - Campbell, Angus 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Center for Advanced Studies in the Behavioral Sciences, The (CASBS) 1960-1967 (Box 3)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS) 1954-1965 (Box 3)
    - Converse, Philip E. 1959-1960 (Box 3)
    - Eldersveld, Samuel J. 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Institute of American Universities 1971-1976 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript Reviews
      - Journal of Politics 1963-1968 (Box 3)
      - American Political Science Review 1963-1966 (Box 3)
      - American Political Science Review 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - American Political Science Review 1969-1972 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1960-1972 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1973-1975 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - Proposal Reviews
      - National Science Foundation: Myron Weiner, Massachusetts Institute of Technology 1970 (Box 4)
      - National Science Foundation: Roper Public Opinion Research Center 1970 (Box 4)
      - National Science Foundation: Miscellaneous 1968-1969 (Box 4)
      - National Science Foundation: Miscellaneous 1970 (Box 4)
      - National Science Foundation: Miscellaneous 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Ranney, Austin 1963 (Box 4)
    - Scheff, Thomas J. 1956-1960 (Box 4)
    - Stokes, Donald E. 1963-1966 (Box 4)
    - Site Visits 1966-1971 (Box 4)
    - Visitors 1963-1972 (Box 4)
  - Chronological
    - 1956 (Box 4)
    - March-August 1957 (Box 4)
    - September-December 1957 (Box 4)
    - January-June 1958 (Box 4)
    - August-December 1958 (Box 4)
    - January-June 1959 (Box 4)
    - July-December 1959 (Box 4)
    - January-April 1960 (Box 4)
    - May-December 1960 (Box 4)
    - 1961 (Box 4)
    - 1962 (Box 4)
    - 1964-1966 (Box 4)